Guide to the Westside Crime Prevention Program Records 1981-2006 MS 2914
New-York Historical Society
Westside Crime Prevention Program records
1981-2006 (bulk 1990-1996)
New-York Historical Society
Westside Crime Prevention Program (New York, N.Y.)
MS 2914
2 Linear feet
This collection documents the aims, internal workings, and external outreach of the Westside Crime Prevention Program, a community-based, not-for-profit organization made up of volunteers who were dedicated to making life on the West Side (from 59th street to 110th street, from the Hudson River to Central Park) safe and secure. The material dates from 1986 to 2006. The Westside Crime Prevention Program Records consists of Board Minutes, newsletters, correspondence and press releases, photographs and ephemera collected from public educational events. In addition, the collection contains program proposals and information concerning organizations associated with the Westside Crime Prevention Program.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in four series, according to the type of document. Series I-III contains records concering the workings of the Westside Crime Prevention Program. Series IV contain other association records of programs that cooperated with the Westside Crime Prevention Program.
Missing Title
Series I: Minutes and Agendas
Series II: Printed Material and Administrative Records
Series III: Photographic Material and Ephemera
Series IV: Other Associations
Historical note
Westside Crime Prevention Program (WCPP) was founded in 1981 by a group of Upper West Siders in response to a rash of street muggings, burglaries, and auto crime. Marjorie Cohen, a freelance writer who was an Upper West Side resident and witness to the crime in the neighborhood, organized and led the progam as Executive Director beginning in 1988 at the height of the crack epidemic on the Upper West Side. WCPP was a community-based, not-for-profit organization made up of volunteers who were dedicated to making life on the West Side (from 59th street to 110th street, from the Hudson River to Central Park) safe and secure. To accomplish this goal, WCPP developed both a Neighborhood Watch Program and a Safe Haven program that were so successful that they have since been used as models throughout the city. WCPP also lobbied for community policing on the Upper West Side and for increased cooperation between police and residents to address drug and crime problems.
Feeling that the core mission of the organization had been fulfilled, Marjorie Cohen and the members of the Westside Crime Prevention Program decided to disband in 2010.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Scope and Contents note
The Westside Crime Prevention Records consist primarily of board meeting minutes and agendas, from 1984 to 2002. The meeting minutes and agendas deal primarily with the organization's program development, financial records, and community outreach.
There is also some correspondence and press releases that document the Westside Crime Prevention Program's accomplishment and cooperation with the New York Police Department. The collection also consists of Westside Crime Prevention Program newsletters, program proposals, educational and training manuals and photographic slides of drug dealings and paraphernalia, documentation concerning the associated organizations that cooperated with the Westside Crime Prevention Program, and ephemera from coordinated neighborhood events.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marjorie Cohen for the Westside Crime Prevention Program, May 2011
Central Park (New York, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- History.; Upper West Side (New York, N.Y.); Upper West Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Children -- New York (State) -- New York.; Community centers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Crime -- New York (State) -- New York.; Criminal law -- New York (State) -- Cases.; Drug Abuse; Drug abuse counseling -- New York (State) -- New York.; Family -- New York (State).; Law -- New York (State).; Poor -- New York (State) -- New York -- Social conditions.; Street life -- New York (State) -- New York.; Streets -- New York (State) -- New York.; Urban renewal -- Citizen participation.; Financial records.; Minutes (administrative records); Slides (photographs).; Cohen, Gail; Cohen, Marjorie; Gersbeck, Joseph T.; Ward, Benjamin; New York (N.Y.). Police Department
- Series I: Minutes and Agendas, 1987-2002
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I consists entirely of the Westside Crime Prevention Program board meeting minutes and agendas, from 1984 to 2002. The meeting minutes and agendas deal primarily with the organization's program development, financial records, and community outreach.
  Arrangement note
  Series I: Board Minutes and Agendas are arranged chronologically.
  - Westside Drug Task Force: Minutes and Agendas, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Westside Drug Task Force: Minutes and Agendas, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Westside Drug Task Force: Minutes and Agendas, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1984, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Board Meetings: Minutes and Agendas, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series II: Print Material and Administrative Records, 1981-2006
  Series II consists of Westside Crime Prevention Program newsletters, correspondence, program proposals, training materials and handbooks. Correspondence highlights include letters from Police Commissioner Benjamin Ward.
  Series II: Print Material and Administrative Records is arranged chronologically.
  - Westside Crime Prevention News, 1981-2006 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and Press Releases, 1987-1997 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Program Proposals, 1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Drug Watch Training Manual, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Conflict Resolution Project: Final Report, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Safe Haven" and "Resolution is the Solution" Informational Guide, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Crime Prevention Community Handbooks, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series III: Photographic Material and Ephemera, 1986-2004, undated
  Series III consists mostly of educational photographic slides of drug dealings in the Upper West Side. There is also a signed photograph of executive director Marjorie Cohen and Mayor Michael Bloomberg, Westside Crime Prevention Program poster and banner, and flyers concerning Westside Crime Prevention community events.
  Arragement note
  Series III: Photographic Material and Ephemera is arranged chronologically.
  - Slides of Drug Dealings, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Slides of Drug Dealings, circa 1988-1993 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Slides of Drug Dealings, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Signed photograph of Marjorie Cohen and Mayor Michael Bloomberg, 27 February 2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Westside Crime Prevention Program Posters and Flyers, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - N.Y.P.D. Gear Guard "Safe Haven" Keychain, undated (Box 4, Object 1)
  - Westside Crime Prevention Program Banner, undated (Box 4, Object 2)
- Series IV: Other Associations, 1988-1997, undated
  Series IV consists of documents relating to other community organizations or programs that cooperated with the Westside Crime Prevention Program.
  Series IV: Other Associations is arranged alphabetically by organization.
  - Central Park Task Force, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Community Board Seven, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Federation of Westside Black Associations: "A Security Manual for the Upper West Side", undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Rent Stabilization Association: "Drug Free Neighborhoods", 1990 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Rent Stabilization Association: "Drug Free Neighborhoods", 1990 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Safe Haven, 1997, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Tactical Narcotics Team, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)